To our constant need for
staggering, winding and witty stories intensified
in the shadow of the farms
is equally indisputably true here and now
a half month into the second year of Pandemin
As it was almost 700 years ago
When Giovanni Boccaccio in his Decamerone
let ten young florentinians escape the bulge
to a country villa there
They told ten stories each,
one nicer than the other
About lurid priests and women who dated in their men the most amazing lies
to get a shepherd's time with their lovers.
During these miserable months
Soon 15
Have we devoured both large and widely landscaped novels
As Lydia Sandgren "Collected works" and Klas Östergren's "Renegates"
And countless television series, which most recently the wonderful "fast cash".
It is with joy and gratitude, a privilege,
that this sunny and chilled spring evening
Get health all you out in the digital Gutenberg galaxy, welcome to the Gothenburg City Library
that sounds good for
When you call him
the most elegant by writers
So he completely agrees with you.
Kjell Westö debuted in 1986 with the poetry collection "Tango Orange"
and got its big breakthrough
ten years later with the novel
"The dragons over Helsinki"
who began a series of independent novels about human fate with the Helsinki of the 20th century
as suggestive
and detailed fund.
In 2013, Westö received the Nordic Council Literature Prize, to name one of many
prestigious awards and awards Westö has been awarded.
He is also a guitarist in
The cover band what
And once upon a time, key players in the Finnish writer's team.
Like Jaques Werup and
Theodor Kallifatides is Kjell Westö a nice example of the fact that musicality and ball mind are
Large assets for a writer.
What does
Kjell Westös
round paintings at one time so accessible and challenged,
is partly, of course,
Prosan's artistically immense distribution of shadows and days,
which is Shakespeare's definition of poetry, donates "Airy nothing. A local habitation and a name."
Partly that they are permeated by the conviction of the power and ability of the story
to explore human life
and its riddles,
Where the present is cohabiting with history like Siamese twins, back to back,
so that at the same time we see the past sucked in and down into the drainage of time
And the future rush us to meet.
At Kjell Westö, every human being is a miracle.
As the last sentence in “Don't go alone in the night” the fourth
the novel in the Helsinki Site, reads in
All melancholy trust.
Speaking of "Don't go alone in the night" you said with empfas in an interview,
When it came out ten years ago 2011 that you were
And now I quote you,
"Finished with Helsinki".
Once for all.
And was even attracted to the idea of becoming
"Minimalist at fifty".
Now
Do I want to ask you:
Ten years and three novels, of which only
"Tritonus" does not have Helsinki as a stage room
later,
Plus a novel project
in progress with Helsinki during the intermediate peace until the continuation war as a fund and
“The sulfur yellow sky” about to become a movie
it seems to me as your narrative voice has made you abandon
the minimalist ambitions,
And getting rid of Helsinki?
Is it true?
Two things I will immediately think about.
One is
the unfortunate thing in always being interviewed, or very often being interviewed, when you have just completed a book
And it has gone into print.
Because then at least I am so pumped so that
I say the most,
what to call it,
I seek empathy in my fatigue and say things of that kind.
When I regain the forces
So it will be as you just explained, differently.
But I just postponed this minimalist dream.
Now it is minimalist at 65.
I'll be there but I've been postponing it for 15 years.
Yes
I love short stories and the fact is that, I'll insert a parenthesis here.
Alongside my novel project that maybe we will come back to later, so I'm going on right now
and writes, along with a writer colleague whose name I do not intend to state,
A short prose book with the working name! The years "where we write short texts
which deals with the passage of time
With offspring
in different years.
And I enjoy
great by writing these
one to four sides
short prose texts that I actually seriously,
This dream of becoming a minimalist has rather
grown and strengthened but as long as the novel ideas
forces me ...
toward the book fair because of the decision to invite
The right -wing extremist magazine New Times.
A decision that incidentally became the origin of a tough
And infected debate on freedom of speech and intellectual responsibility.
How do you view that problem and that position today?
In this with your wording a letter to your writer colleague Juha Itkonen
quote:
Where humanity seems fully partly part
As for the longing for, on the one hand, a freedom and solidarity society,
On the other hand, a tyrannical and authoritarian.
How would you
Relate to this today?
Then autumn 2017,
The debate had started long before, it had started in the spring of 2017 or maybe even in the winter of 2017
I grasped after great anguish and very pondering
The choice to
Go to Gothenburg
Book Fair 2017 and
Make resistance to Nazism and fascism in that way.
Then it became a pretty hot debate
There were young colleagues who even
accused us who went for being some kind
runners to dark forces, right -wing extremist forces.
It swed, can i say, for i'm
So sworn antinazi and anti -fascist as you can become.
It was then
if
What one thought was the right way to resist
Against the dark forces.
I made the decision after great anguish that decision, and therefore it was so important
When I had free moments at the fair
Vacant moments so
I went out on the heath,
For the alternative fair and for demonstrations because that was where I belonged.
Yes
In summary
Many years later
I think nothing is won.
Nothing gets won by
that people who are basically on the same page
for betrayal and for
wrong decisions. This is very important, we know from history, so many times
in history has
These good forces that are just a little disagreed for each other.
You are almost blinded for where the darkness really comes from.
Don't let the Nazi tree obscure the Social Democratic Forest, like the German
Communist leader Ernst Thälmann once said.
Which we know what led to.
We know that.
Germany, late 20s,
Early 30s are a good example of just that.
Polarization might have started a little sneakily in the past
But then the positions were locked.
One must say that under
the four, five last years have
It exploded, so much has happened.
It has been tumultuous years.
A result of
The tumultuous world we live in today.
Right -wing extremism has emerged in Europe in a way that I at least, if you had told me when I was young at
The 1980s and 90s like this will go, so I had not believed.
No,
already
Now it really
Ultralight
position.
It is much, much stronger forces and much more thoughtful forces in motion now.
So it has gone.
For us 20th-century people who both you and I are, it is a few years, but we originate
from the same time, I think that too many of us
so the new millennium's first two decades have been
Let's call it an absurdity's progress that has become more and more bizarre and difficult to understand.
Our thoughts, our performance worlds
stands in relief against World War II.
It was the big story that preceded us.
I was born 5 years after the war and my grandfather was a Jew so I always heard if Hitler won the war you had
not been born.
Which was quite heavy when you were five.
To study the story has for me been a
It's a given
and
a necessity.
For me, it wasn't a matter of course first.
I was born a little later, 1961,
And as a really young, I tried to dive into Anglo -Saxon popular culture and as well as pretending to
I was born long after the Second World War and that it
Don't really affect me that much.
This was so terribly thought error, partly purely chronologically because I was born
Sixteen years after the Second World War ended.
What is sixteen years old, it's nothing.
So I also came from a family where both grandfather and grandmother had fallen down in the wars.
To think the way I tried to do when I was 15, 20 years old, I discovered then when
I became an adult for real, so I discovered that it was not sustainable.
Because that's exactly as you say.
It is the great tragic story that exists as a fund for our generation
Own experiences.
A fallen grandfather and a fallen grandfather.
Because Finland de facto was
Germany's allies,
that it was not
Equally obvious
positions and that they
conditioned a prize in social and private life.
Was it so?
That
Very complicated.
That what a thing we Finland
Had very difficult to meet.
We all had sorts, when I was a child for example
and went to school and grew up there were all possible
theories
built around this that would
as well as liberate us from the realization that we had been Germany's
Allies.
That we waged a separate war against the Soviet Union between 1941-1944
There was a theory called Driver theory,
which is about small nations
are so powerless
In the great swirls of history
compared with
But it was also a time when it is very difficult to find,
In Sweden you have spoken
Much about the debt that existed in allowing transit, etc.
It is a theme that has been difficult.
I have not written myself
so much.
I actually avoid writing
novels about the war itself just because my
Grandfather had fallen and there has been a trauma in my family.
There has been a lot of Finnish fiction in recent years
who are now trying to treat all of these
German Wermacht that was up in Lapland, how we treated
Soviet prisoners of war and that kind of ...
This I think for us unspoken to just
"Hägring 38"
It is a novel that with Helsinki as a fund
If any people in the Finnish -Swedish bourgeoisie living in a time
as
Is uncomfortably similar to our own but you do not write the reader on the nose.
Which makes it even more
Effective.
And there the dream of purity and community
brought the world to the edge of the abyss.
Those among you out there in cyber space that to adventure not
read “Hägring 38”
can i promise you have a
Completely decisive reading experience ahead of you.
That novel is an artistic complete testimony
about the ambivalence as right and position on the major questions of time,
an obligation.
In your “work diary” from the
years you worked with “Hägring 38” which is now
afterword in the new edition
How to describe your difficulties and efforts to find the right path into the story
About lawyer Thune and the other gentlemen in the Wednesday Club,
that discussion forum
The story revolves around.
You complain that the scenes lacked charge and forward movement as
the thriller -like intrigue requires,
Until you shifted the focus from the gentlemen to Thunes secretary, Matilda Wiik.
That gets haunted by memories from the civil war starvation
When she was a young girl.
This is when you realize that you have to shorten the time shaft
For the story now.
You write:
I have stretched the time shaft as a chewing gum and placed the scenes too far apart.
Instead, you let Matilda in the opening scene
ride a tram through the city after the end of the work day
with their little everyday dreams
and secrets that are also
Finland.
Is the foundation and rough work of creating root systems for the background stories that make the people you depict
three -dimensional,
so that they think, speak, act and react
both in a unique personal and at the same time timely way,
that they do not become anachronistic,
Does that work become more extensive the more distant in time
A story is played out?
Attorney Tune counter
Thomas Brander, the star conductor who is the main character in your new novel "Tritonus"?
The answer is yes.
I have written
I have written about the early 1900s that I
Obviously, not having any experience of my own because I was born in 1961.
Research is more demanding
than when I write
The second main type of novels I have written that have sometimes been pure contemporary novels such as "Tritonus".
Or as novels that take off in, for example, 1950s and 60s and late
moves through the decades until the present.
It's easier.
It requires a lot of research as well and the risk of anachronisms and
Failure with time depiction also exists when writing about a time you have experienced yourself.
There is
A trap in that you may think it is too easy.
The memory is deceitful.
But in some sense it is easier to have your own pictures
A separate visual world to pour out.
When you then write about,
The farther behind it goes there is there,
There are like traps
Already in everyday life.
Things you might not think about having to ...
It's not just about studying the so -called great story, knowing
What the political developments looked like, the big lines.
It is also about that
Learn to understand how people's everyday lives saw.
And it is demanding.
I am doing a novel
that takes place in early January 1940
This banging winter
Cch when I had written 20 pages and was actually not in Finland but in Stockholm,
Had I assumed that Sweden had already started to darken then
their cities.
Until I suddenly found
a source where it emerged that you only test dark
during some short periods in 1940.
Then I have to write about
the entire section and light the street lights and remove the blackout curtains.
This type of trap is there.
There I have an awful admiration for
Author who depicts Bellman's life or Emperor Hadrian.
I do not experience problems with the historical because I still move so close to modern times.
My admiration for those who can write
whether the Viking Age or if the Middle Ages or if the Renaissance is very large.
There, like the distance between our everyday lives and their everyday lives, is still greater.
You would probably appreciate
Very deep Ernst Brunners
suite
About the 18th century, Anckarström,
Sergel.
It's a long line of novels that
which is literally very high.
I have read one, the one about Bellman I have read and it thought I was amazing.
The latest about Sergel, the "marble morm"
I think the best so far.
Another danger, I can imagine, with the nearby or
the rather nearby
the end 60s,
when I was young.
I'm born 50, I had perfect timing
For the late 60's.
I was 12
When the Beatles came up
On ten-in-top with Love Me Do.
as
Made me keep the pace in my way to the adult world.
Then you were 17 years old when
The festival in Monterey, 19 years when Woodstock was ...
I sometimes got the question then when I wrote novels about the 60s and 70s,
If I have been born any other Åe or in any other epoch,
When would I like to be born?
Then I answer for a while that I would have liked to have been born ten years earlier, ie 195.
So had I been a teenager
When everything happened in the music, for example in the 60s.
So I usually add that I have a very weak character and
is quite moody and easy to influence
so i think too i
were rescued from flipping out
in different ways by being born ten years later.
Another danger may be that
MAN
Getting so fond
A era like it!
That you,
If one is not yourself
Has your own experiences
Right timed
Strangering
almost.
So much time markers.
An exciting thing is to
I had a theory that realistically placed writers
often think it
epoch or the decade
As they have been children
is the most magical there is.
And for me, it's the 60s.
However, I have always failed, I think, or at least partially failed, by portraying
It 1980s
where I myself was
Young.
When I read it
Here in winter winter Lydia Sandgren's "Collected works",
she is so young so she
was born in the shift between the 80s and 90s.
She portrays the 80s
with the same feeling for the magic of the 80's
As I always have
Viljat achieved and hoped to have achieved with the 60s.
While I have thought, what the 80s, what is there to portray there?
Suddenly there is where the shimmer and magic there.
It is an outstanding debut.
We read historical novels even
counterfactic.
I read here
the French writer Laurent Binet's novel "Civilization",
a counterfactic novel where he turns on this colonial history steak
and sounds an incentive on the run after a defeat in a war of throne
lay down
in the 1530s.
We read
All historical novels with the facts in hand.
But
The fact that, unlike the Roman designs, we know how it will end is not a problem in itself.
On the contrary, increases
the power of power for the people you read about,
Before their confusion and the future fate of the world, the story's charge for me.
As we said before, culturally impronged elements today
will be threat to the people's tribe tomorrow
And become sub -people who must be eradicated the day after tomorrow.
That's how we know that
It was what happened.
And in “the sulfur yellow sky”
takes your nameless storyteller with the reader
on a
Absolutely incredible journey from it ended the sixties, which was mine,
to our time as you call, I quote,
"A black future cave where the violence and the upcoming wars moved like flickering shadows".
Is it then
For you an obligation
for the art, for you as a writer
Which is bigger than the art?
A direct responsibility for the story?
I am also a political man, a political writer in some sense, even if I am not
party political or
pronounced ideological.
Whether I write historically
About the 20th century
horrors and wrongdoing or more in contemporary
I feel that one has one
Responsibility as a realistic novelist.
For example, when I write about
Finland's 20th century history that was so complex and complicated and so brutal.
We first had a civil war
where we also got free from Russia
and then were forced to fight two wars against the Soviet Union and then
must
our tired army in 1944-45 chase out wehrmacht out
Lapland.
That story
are so complex and bloody and
have influenced all families and families in Finland, there are none
related or family that goes free
or has avoided being affected
of this.
This means that when you write about those times you have a responsibility.
You find and you fabricate.
But I have been very careful
Think so ...
I've ever answered,
Or said
that I write about events,
I use a plausibility theory.
I am writing about events that could have happened, which in all likelihood
Has also happened.
So you have a responsibility.
I would not be able to, for example, become a historical satirist,
Write a historical satire.
I see where I go deep in the people and
My people are fictional but they are founded in that book I write about.
And I sincerely hope I make them and the book fair.
One of the major challenges is,
For example, not to apply our time of aftermath
When I for example
wrote "Hägring 38" so is
several of these
The men in the Wednesday Club,
They lean strongly to the right and are even Nazi attached.
They do not have the facts on hand.
It is easy to judge them afterwards but
In countries such as Finland and Sweden in the late 1930s had the bourgeoisie
Old connections to Germany.
Germany had been the cultural nation par Excellence
Together with France
in Europe.
After the Versaille peace.
It made people not ... it contributed to blindness
In front of what Hitler's Germany
Actually was.
For many things went up far too late.
I have to write these figures.
I remember some sentences I wrote
felt rugged to write
in order to
I have to write them without facts on hand.
As I have.
That is, the Nazi regime was
closest to total evil.
Sometimes and now here during the conversation I start getting for me
that you have chopped into my brain to
it leads step by step along the path
As I have cleared up.
May I postpone one thing, Laurence Binet's book "Civilizations",
I have read reviews of that book in the Swedish Press and it exists
high up on my reading list because I have all my
Life, I read as a child,
There was some boy book series that was played on the Yucatan Peninsula
In Mexico?
Yes!
And also even older cultures.
I wrote about "civilizations" in the Post of Gothenburg
You can probably find that if you google.
That the Inka culture would have invaded Europe
in the 16th century and applied their
Norms, it's fascinating, I want to see what Binet has done from it.
Yes, it's a lot of fun, it's entertaining.
There is a lot about Umberto Eco.
Now we're going to have fun with the story and
Sometimes it runs away and the historical references and parallelizations and
the reversals
Some too many.
But it is a very schwung,
And just like in your novels, enormously throughout.
He is a relatively new writer so he ...
You can give him the Benefit of the Doubt, in terms of self -delight.
Avoiding self -delight takes a whole author life.
Yes!
When we get into this with solidarity towards
the characters, the people,
your figures,
as
is one of your
Main characteristic as a writer.
It is absolutely crucial to me as a reader, my conviction is that the art, the literature
can give a deeper understanding of history and our own location
In the ongoing story,
by shaping
individual unique people's fate on their own terms.
To see the world and time from within with their eyes
in all their complexity and deficiency.
Lars Ahlin formulated
The artistic solidarity
with the people being embodied
like this:
"It is important to exceed without abandoning."
What is your opinion of this?
Do you share that view of the author as the narrator's task?
Or have I just projected my own conviction of the art's and literature
role
On your novels?
I don't think so, I think we share
That's what I can feel now when I
turns 60 this summer.
I think I have some really good novels in me yet but may not be infinitely many.
So the pursuit I have left and where I want to reach even further is to reach even deeper in the people.
Whether I write in the present,
in the same time or if I
writes historically.
Then I can be 10 years old,
11 years
minus
10 days
Older than you are, certify that your novels
know more about aging
than you do yourself.
It is not something you recommend to young people.
That is very nice,
It's like,
It is also one thing that in some way was the point
Absolutely true!
It is actually
The smallest common denominator for all interesting authorship.
To those as with
Lars Ahlin
exceeds without abandoning.
Yes, it is very nice.
I have read some of Lars Ahlin but I did not know that quote, it is very nice.
He has also written "Write weakly about the weak"
Lars Ahlin is for me one of the absolute
Biggest, ever at all.
Open letters to Juha Itkonen you write that you started writing
your new novel "Tritonus"
Autumn
16 and knew from the beginning that you wanted to place the story in the border zone
between present and future.
The novel was virtually finished already in January
null
But when the Corona epidemic turns from threat to reality, you write,
Did you have to do something for the novel's
Time axis.
Here's how you write: I immediately realized that a 2020 without the pandemic, there is.
Not anywhere in the world.
So I started reworking the time shaft.
I didn't just move it,
I also stretched
out it in time to a vague
Postpandemic time there
Fear still
Pyr.
In other words,
in historical novels
through research
Do you do background studies
to saturate your characters.
In this contemporary story you give the nerve and forward -looking energy
by
stretch
The timeline in
in a
vague near future.
This is, you write,
The most faustic I have had to do as a writer.
I think many
with me out there, in front of their computers and toads
Like to hear you describe
in which the faustic in the extended time axis consists,
a little closer?
It was like this,
when the novel, as you just said
Then I have the habit of doing one last processing, often my books come out in August,
September, then I do one last processing in the spring and it has almost always been purely linguistic.
But now I sat with a contemporary novel there ...
Tritonus is divided into one
autumn department,
Half of the book will be played in the fall from October to December.
And the other half in summer
In June, July.
it was
Yet in
January 2020, it was autumn 2019 and summer 2020.
Local rock band The Rainbow played, they went to chamber music festivals.
It was European football for men and Finland
National team was present for the first time.
There were references to it as well.
I realized that this is not possible!
Then I had worked
for four years with this novel and absolutely did not want
that it would go to waste.
So I did the only thing possible, you can't, this is also one of the secrets of novel writing.
Once you have created a path
so you have entered
Time also in the people, also in the subtitle, also between the lines.
So you can't push the time back.
But what could be done was stretching out the time shaft and moving the story.
It still takes off in 2016, 2015
And the terrorist attack in Brussels for example.
As conductor Brander only escapes with distress and scarcity.
So I simply reached it out so that it takes place in somewhere near future and when I wrote
the story
So I thought, okay this is maybe autumn 20 and summer 2.
Then none of us knew,
a year ago,
Now it has dragged out on time, so now I think that "Tritonus" may be playing out
Autumn 22, summer 23.
Another factor
that did that
Not the light mind though
The illusion of ours
relative invulnerability,
That the illusion
Was born out
The welfare society that Pandemin revealed had been demolished.
And plundered out
and was cut up and
sold out to lowest bidder for 25 years.
Now we suddenly saw that it did not hold.
The dam did not hold.
The dams burst.
I think that also had a great influence on
the Swedish
Pandemist strategy.
Matt it also had its material causes.
This
Mumlandet
and
The handcuff unit.
Well...
I would say, if I can comment,
would I say that
There has been so much revolving things in the world the latest
the years but even before the pandemic
explodes the climate crisis, which in itself has long existed in people's consciousness,
Thanks in large part to Greta Thunberg.
And these two things together,
cutting awareness of the climate crisis of most of us
and the pandemic, has done,
At least I think that
sometime in 2016, 2015, that human, r
Many people with resources thought it was everyday
to
Go on five days
Weekly holidays to Bali or
Constantly new big cities around the world.
We had built something that
could not hold.
We would remember that there was something that was built for
Hardly even a per thousand of the people of the world.
It was the richest minority.
That promil
liver
on borrowed money, on borrowed time.
Alex Schulman wrote a pretty nice column,
Where is he writing, is it in Expressen?
Yes
Just a few weeks ago when it has the giant container had settled across the Suez Canal
He wrote that it was the ultimate picture for what we have done.
We built
a ship so large that it is not accommodated
Worldwide.
One of
your features
as a writer
is
that you
Never write
The reader on the nose
Without establishing
your time rooms and your characters
indirectly
Like after all
Life works.
They are there with their experiences, with their dreams,
with their failures, with their confusion.
And that is what makes them three -dimensional.
You're not talking about
that this is a human being that
is confused and not
know ...
And faces a situation that he or she cannot master.
The indirect way you establish.
This way of establishing your characters and your stories indirectly
Do you show in the introduction to
"Tritonus"
where I
have asked you to read up
A section to demonstrate this.
I'll do that.
Here is a short section from the beginning of the novel "Tritonus"
The beginning of subscription time
A bit away
Near the plot limit
Low the sauna up on its rocky hob.
It was not bad either
With glass rooms and kitchenette and extra shower room.
Branders childhood friend, architect Sandmark
had also designed a whirlpool
which has been cast into a sink into the mountain outside.
Wide wooden stairs with solid rails led down to the beach and
There were new coffin bridges at both guest cottage and sauna.
The place had cost the fire 700,000 euros
And after the new building and renovations it would be even more
Although property prices have fallen significantly.
He had a hard time understanding that he was still so rich
And even harder to understand why it didn't make him happier.
All he owned felt like someone else's
and he wasn't happy
But not afraid.
When he opened the front door, a bat flew into the living room.
At first he thought it was a little bird.
But it was the wrong kind of silence and the wrong kind of wing bat.
He understood that it must be a leather patch.
Somewhere he had read that they paired in the fall and slept through the winter and then the fertilization took place with delayed
Effect in the spring.
Shouldn't they have pulled away for wintering already?
But it had been a warm autumn.
Probably there were still plenty of insects.
The bats could eat many hundreds per night.
He knew they are stained
And that the bite spread severe illnesses.
He lit all the lights and the bat flew restlessly back and forth,
stroked tightly past his face.
It did it time and time again,
avoided him with the help of his radar.
He knew it was screaming all the time
at a frequency almost no human could hear, how musical
She was.
Brander Rös and followed the bat with the gaze and
Saw how it sat high on the wall.
He took the garbage brush and poked on the animal with the shaft
The leather patch was left, dry and grayish brown
And motionless and he considered pressing it with the brush, kill it.
He thought of the blind will to survive-
The one found in all living
and on the bite and on the diseases
And didn't dare.
but
he has not been confronted
with the big dangers.
We also know that the illnesses he is talking about,
We know what disease it is.
It's the pandemic.
Its mythical beginning, its mythical emergence.
So does
That we know
This is a fading memory.
This with the bats
And the diseases
faded
as memory.
That was exactly what I was looking for.
I think so
is a fantastic,
Brilliant and illustrative
example
On how
you
tells
in a way that makes the people
and your story
retains their secrets.
You don't serve everything at once
Without it, the kitchen path comes in.
It blows in through the window in shape
by a bat.
I think that is one of the reasons for your novels
is permanent.
Now I realize
As I listen to you now I realize that I never answered,
I gave a very indirect
and not entirely detailed answer to your question what it was that was so faustically
Last spring with move
Time in Tritonus to the near future.
The faustic was, of course, that while I sat and did it
grew
pandemic and became increasingly ravaged around the world and people became ill and died.
There I sat.
Then I didn't have this work room but I sat
In another part of Helsinki
Well strict and harsh words,
I mean enough
that Tomas Brander
also
is one
complex and contradictory man with qualities that make him
host
get to know.
I mean that too.
What was it that made you choose to place your story about the sore but gryended friendship between
him, the famous artist
And that movement out of cities
And the cures.
But
There must be another reason too?
Where you are tired of Helsinki?
No, I'm not tired of Helsinki but we should remember, we are on the right track here so to
The idea and novel construction started even before the pandemic.
Then it has actually happened, there is an escape, most recently today I saw a heading in a newspaper,
If relocation from all Nordic capitals
All Nordic capitals lose the number of inhabitants.
But this I didn't know when I started
Write the novel
2016, without it was
a personal
Prolonged dream it was about.
The environment in the world that
I think I feel
Very strong
for,
Further to Helsinki,
is the southern Finnish archipelago.
I have been lucky enough to spend not only spent summers but also autumn and spring in the archipelago ever since 1988,
for almost 33 years.
First i had over 20 years
a cabin on an island
and then
I divorced and
Everything must be rebuilt.
Now i have had in
Five to six years, cottage on another island.
So I dreamed for many years about writing an archipelago novel.
To place a novel this
small
maybe in a way more
easy -to -handle community where things become very clear
Compared to the diversity and complexity of the big city.
So it's an old
personal
Author dream I have
realized when I have placed “Tritonus” in
The archipelago instead of in Helsinki.
Helsinki is there
in Branders and others' memory.
Both Brander and Lindell were born and raised in Helsinki but
Helsingborg certainly plays a minor role this time.
But I'm not tired of town
and the novel I have now started and hope to complete in a few years
it is settled again in
A historic Helsinki.
I thought we would end now.
It begins to suffer towards its end.
I would
the time room
from mid -March 1940
until midsummer 1941 when the continuation war starts.
What is well called in Finnish history.
It is called the intermediate peace in Finnish history writing, yes.
A very fragile
such.
Maybe the story comes, now I'm right in the beginning so I can't
say something confident.
I can not either
say too much, because there comes the writer's crash,
The author's skepings in.
If I talk to the book I will not be able to
Write it.
But
Just this time axis, possibly I continue a bit into the continuing war, maybe this fall
null
I have avoided wars ,, as I already said in my novels for
that grandfather and grandfather died there and it has been so
loaded in my family.
But now the year then
I turn 60 so I feel ready.
But I go a bit a detour because I write about this one
fragile, remarkable period of
some kind of peace or ceasefire with the Soviet Union we had between March 40
and
27,000 men had already died
When to do agricultural work in the summer of 1940, there were like gaps everywhere.
It needed more
Finnish .... than ever for
on many farms
The sons have not come home.
It is a very strange time
I want to try to portray it as I usually do through
Apparently quite everyday people and their fate.
My wife and i
spent,
were in the countryside, in the house on the countryside
from the end of March to
A week, ten days into August, almost all the time.
For quarantine reasons.
Every now and then we had to go into town.
It was an extremely peculiar experience.
The whole town,
What one associates with town,
life, movement,
cafes,
Where was out of play.
In Sweden it was light, after all,
compared to somewhere else.
But
Yet it was this one
silence, this silent spring
for this new novel there
Helsinki is
trapped,
cut off,
silent.
In the letter I wrote you to Itkoinen I describe a beautiful but icy April evening
Last year.
We then had a very strict Lockdown
in Helsinki.
So I live on Skatudden which is a very centrally located
neighborhood
right next to Helsinki,
At the heart of Helsinki City.
I went, this cold
But sunny April night I went in
to the center and walked along the Esplanad Park and Alexandersgatan and I have to say that as
native Helsinki and a man who was still in love with his hometown, I was close
to start crying.
It was dead.
It was like after one,
When in our youth you talked about the fear of hydrogen bomb, the bomb that would remove all people but leave the buildings intact.
That's what it looked like.
You sat there with notes with notes and that it goes terribly sluggish ...
Is there any single
sentence
from any one of these pieces of paper
as you could
Drown you
To read up?
In order to in that case we would be
First in the world!
Don't you dare?
I have inside the machine some, but I dare not, no!
There goes the limit for this author's procedure!
If I do, it's run!
But since I read everything you write
So I don't think I need it either!
I've been there so many times
And in so many different eras.
But I shall remedy
This gap in my formation.
If you come over, I offer a glass!
I hope so!
Have a good Kjell!
Bye!
Hello!